[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
all right everyone welcome to the stoa
i am peter limberg the steward of the
stoa and it still has a place for us to
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the nice edge of this moment
and for those new faces uh here today or
watching this on youtube no one knows
what the store is
some call it a digital campfire a
communal podcast a wisdom gym
uh it's better not to know i sense one
thing we do know is it is a place that
we do not talk about stoicism
um and today we have
keith johnstone with us uh keith is a
pioneer of the
improv theater movement uh he's known
for an inventing uh the impro system
and the author of uh this legendary book
impro
um and his work has kind of formed a
cult status uh and a wider audience that
extends well beyond the theater
community
uh finkadesh rao from ribbon farm i'll
read a quote uh
from him when you wrote about keith's
book impro is ostensibly a book about
improv and the theater depending on
where you're coming from it might be
no more than that or it might be a near
religious experience
so how today is going to work
keith and i are going to chat for maybe
about 10 to 20 minutes
and if you have any questions throw them
in the chat box um
i'll call you unmute yourself ask your
question to keith if you don't want to
be on youtube because this will be on
youtube just indicate that
um and i'll read on your behalf can i
tell you afterwards
how's it going keith oh you mean it goes
out live on youtube
uh it goes afterwards on youtube after
can i tell you afterwards
so how are you doing today i'm okay
ah where are you speaking from
i'm from toronto canada and yeah
a couple of hours away from us yeah just
just a few
um so i thought i'd ask uh like a really
broad question to start with
um and feel free to swat it away or ask
me that
the sound is cut out someone muted me
uh yeah um i thought i'd ask you a
general question to start with
um and feel free to swat it away or ask
something or ask me to ask you something
more specific
um i thought it'd be good just inquire
into your life's work
like if someone is coming new to it and
i imagine that people in this room are
how would you describe your system or
your book impro
it's been called a system ever since
to raise produced a book on me
but i don't really see it as being a
system i see it more as an attitude of
mind
uh i don't see improvisation
i don't see improvisation it makes me
annoyed now
it's not what i wanted i
detest light entertainment i think it's
terrible
i think it's a byproduct of the
education system i think is a
revulsion against education basically
all those hours and hours in school of
organized boredom
um unhappy teachers and happy kids
so i think that stress is attached to
learning
so for pleasure
it's a sort of alien concept to a lot of
people
to to relax they have to have light
entertainment
which basically teaches nothing
like chatting to actresses on late night
shows or whatever
i mean david letterman's
um producer did say and i quote quoting
if you learn anything of value from
watching our program we've failed in our
purpose
as i think knowledge it's very difficult
to get rid of the uh curiosity of an ape
but a lot of adults a lot of professors
in the university were really not
curious
i mean that they suffered so much
learning and stuff
that they just want to go and have a
beer in the pub
something to calm them down so i think
i did find a thing on the tv the other
day if you
typed in michael moore and finland and
education you'd find it
about the finns who at one time had the
brightest students in
the world i think it's not true anymore
but
it must have gone to japan where they
flogged them
but they cancelled homework and they
adjusted four hours a day
they tried to make education pleasurable
and instead of ripping the slaves to the
to the mill so
i'm not sure was that a question
whatever it was i liked your response
so i'm just going to pivot to the
questions in the chat right now because
we have a lot
uh elred you have a question for keith
if you're going to mute yourself
um yeah so
i just heard you say that uh your
work is not a system and shouldn't be
used like that
how would you like to see your work used
well
i think it's like a wheel with spokes
and some of the spokes are mine
and you pick a spoke and you're trying
to get to the center of the wheel and if
one spoke starts working you move to
another one
and you try absolutely anything for once
it's a system it's like
we start with this and we go to that and
we go to this
and you can have a syllabus um
they have syllabuses in drama teaching
they'll have three three months on
improvisation
somewhere near the beginning in the
course
which is crazy because of course you
should improvisation should be part of
the whole process
from beginning to end you shouldn't
isolate it for three months maybe
a week of improvisation and then you
refer back to it
and gradually increase the knowledge
so i don't think you can really have a
syllabus for improvisation and
universities of course in colleges
always want that
and schools want that and it's not the
nature of the beast
hello hello
yeah yeah
alright do you have any follow-up
i guess not i i think wheel and spoke
answers my question
and keep going back to the wheel
and spending time spending the time that
it
the beast requires i think that's my
question
all right uh maybe gray
you're up next hi
keith i'm so excited that you're here uh
so appreciative
that you'd uh be willing to visit our
little community
um i've studied uh psychology
and a lot of what i learned in uh
lifestyle and developmental psychology
was that children learn
through playing but something that i
didn't see emphasized in that context
was that we all learn through playing
and so i was wondering uh if you have an
opinion about
for you what the most important
connection between playing and learning
is
well
you can make anything you can make
anything into a game
and you can be playful
[Music]
i think when i was 11 some
teacher probably still suffering from
post-traumatic stuff from the great war
um a man with no joy in his life
he should have been treated i think he
came in and he wrote the world algebra
on the blackboard
and he said you've had it easy up till
now now this is going to be really
difficult
what a guy on the other hand
when einstein was about four or five
he just he had this nice uncle
who said there was this game we're going
to play where you hunt
feature called x and when you capture it
it has to tell you its name
so there you can see two two ends of the
candle or whatever two ends of the rod
twins of the
cane the nice end and the nasty end
but a lot of my education with my
ex-soldiers
so there it was a sort of military
attitude where you just had to obey and
do it
um
me and another boy were given some
physics experiment to
to measure the uh to time the cooling of
boiling water
god that's boring but
and then he said join join up between
all the points
smoothly and all of ours were slightly
off
so we did curving lines to join up the
points
and the physics master the reverence me
came and yelled at us for
doing that but he could have said hey
that's amazing
i've never seen results like this before
could you check them again that's
astounded my god
you may be onto something here i mean
if you could have a playful attitude so
but no but the finns seem to have
conquered that
they seem to understood
i haven't worked in finland for a long
time so it probably wasn't me
i did read a book called summer hill
once you may know about that
i can't remember now i'm so old i can't
remember any names
neil neil yes
but the one thing about neil is that he
just wanted
children to be democratic and to have a
good time
but he didn't think it was abnormal if
they didn't have a passion for learning
and i would say if you don't have a
passion for learning you're severely
damaged
and that damage should be healed
yeah it's it's strange to me how in like
formal public education so often
playing is considered the disruption to
learning
and not the path to it and it's nice to
see people
like you who are able to recognize that
that's not the most natural way of
looking at it
so thank you so much
all right we have uh
robin hansen uh past guests of the stoa
um robin if you can unmute yourself
hi there nice to meet you um you are
mentioned in our book the elephant in
the brain if you'd ever like to check it
out
um my question is uh in psychology when
people talk about status
they distinguish usually two kinds of
status there's dominance and prestige
you have a lot of insightful commentary
in your book about status moves but you
don't
distinguish status and dominance and
prestige
do status moves differ according to
those kinds of status or not
and if so how well
i was a shy young man when i did all
this stuff
and i didn't want to shout dominate and
submit
i mean i wouldn't feel that was my style
at the actors so i decided to call it
status
but and i guess it's like jargon in a
way i tried to avoid jargon
in my view the status is what you do to
somebody else
it's not what you are so in theater
quite often the especially in theater of
the absurd
high status people will play low status
to the slave or something
uh they get the they exploit the wrong
status for laughs or
tragic things it's
there's that great japanese thing like
going through the gate
i think kurosawa did two versions of it
but i'm getting sidetracked
but where the the servant
beats up the master who's dressed
as a servant as they go through the gate
at some moment when the deception is
about to be discovered
but anyway it's part of theater
but i think we were shocked
this all this information was well known
as it was
certainly from research in 1922 in
denmark on danish chickens
uh it's just and it's
it's a blindingly obvious thing is once
you know that
is to teach it teach actors to
change their level of status and
it was unconsciously known about all
good playwrights
good plays are demonstrations of status
transactions really
most people can't write plays because
they think it's literature
and also they won't have the characters
altered
i mean drama is that one person changes
another or you don't have any drama
one of the reasons i'm brought stiff by
improvisation is that nobody's ever
changed
they're frightened so they go on the
stage to be strong
and they somehow think that means not to
be altered
so it's not a very dramatic form mostly
people singing songs or
improvising songs or making jokes but
nothing ever happens
this happens in drama means someone's
altered
shakespeare was very good at that
if you tell the nun you're going to
execute her brother
unless she [ __ ] you
that's going to cause some changes but
not in improvisation
then none will say not again
and protect herself because if she says
not again she doesn't have to be altered
or macbeth shakespeare has him
incredibly altered
he comes in to the feast with and sees
duncan's ghosts and he gets carried out
feet first i mean
you can't be more altered than that but
so can i follow up uh peter yeah yeah
so um it sounds like you're mostly
talking about dominance when when you're
talking but let me give a concrete
example so you can clarify according to
the usual norms
if somebody is dominant it's not okay to
look directly at their eyes
because that's a challenge to them and
they have to respond
to your challenge but if they're
prestigious it's okay to look directly
at them and that's
that's acceptable because uh you know
you are admiring them
and celebrating them by looking at them
so which of those two
is a status move i think all the books
are wrong about this
uh well maybe not now
back in the 60s my god what a long time
ago
back in the 60s i think it said if you
the person who looks away first is the
weaker
but in fact if you look away first the
message can be
i'm not afraid of you i can ignore you
well teachers have a special status
where they
can look into eyes but they mustn't look
for too long into anybody's eyes
but let me hand losing this track here
pro
gentleman um it's
the thing is if you look away from
somebody and you take a quick look back
that's devastating but they didn't say
that in those days maybe they do now
but you can try it you look away from
someone and you're strong
you take quick looks back and you
start to crumble physically
that's that's it it's more complicated
this eye thing than people think
uh and the blinking is so important
we're counting the blink rate all the
time something
something in us is counting the blink
rate
yes does that answer your question
a bit enough
all right uh status is in many forms
it's not just one thing it's like
there's what the body expresses
you can be dominant with a very
submissive body
uh like a
savage [ __ ] taking down some
aristocrat uh
it's it's not just one set of things
it's
it's the whole animal it's nothing a
human being does
which doesn't tend to affect the power
between them
when i was young they didn't seem to
know why there was a kinetic dance
that is between human beings if you film
them secretly
and speed up the film afterwards it
looks like they're dancing because
one person uh relates their body
movements to the other persons
and it's really i wanted to ask desmond
morris that i didn't
i was gonna have dinner with him but i
just had a long talk with him in a taxi
his sister was ill
it was on my list of things to ask
because he said the kinetic dance was
timed within a
45th of a second which is ridiculous and
i couldn't imagine why it would have
evolved to be so fast
except it is life or death uh
but i mean if you if you put your hand
out like that
oh yeah yes okay
it's totally different than doing it
like that
somebody used to teach politicians to do
that
oh obama was interesting because he was
a community organizer
and he didn't want to be dominant when
he started
and they all said he wasn't presidential
enough for about a year
and he used to waggle his head about and
he would make gestures with the thumb
alongside the hand and
his solution was to make less gestures
but
if some of the totals put your thumb out
he could have yeah it would have been
nice to do
but anyway i think
all politicians should probably have
acting lessons
or at least lessons in this stuff
and clever ones do but they don't always
get the nicest acting teachers
i mean clinton obviously had some speech
there at this to come in
because in the end he could talk without
losing his voice
all right um i'll take in my fellow meta
tribalist tyler uh you're up next
uh so i woke up this morning and i was
trying to find myself
and it turned out that i was somewhere
between
my neck and the top of my scalp which
was interesting because that's not my
entire body
and then when i asked for contributions
to my sense of consciousness from the
rest of my body i found that
my lower body was higher status than my
upper body
and that i became a totally different
person also when i integrated the two
and
uh put them less to war and so this is
the
the thing i read about in your book that
struck me the most the moving of the eye
around or of basic consciousness or
something like that
um and typically when i have people try
it put their eye
in their finger or at the other end of
the room they have a psychedelic
experience what about this one with the
the silver ball in the chest the silver
boy poking out light
a silver ball i haven't tried it in your
chest
we should pump you light out try that
that's really that's the most positive
very intense it's fun you should try
try to parties try it in bars and you
get served quicker
yeah i was going to play a hero
if you want to play hamlet or siegfried
or somebody you know a high status
person
it opens your chest up and it i guess
manic
i sometimes i can't do this much but i
sometimes wake up
and try not to move the muscle that's
weird well when you wake up you move a
muscle
to take possession of the body again you
know like it's what you do
nobody wakes up and doesn't move a
muscle
but if you can possibly not do it then
you enter a slightly odd state
anywhere but i have various forms of fun
which may not be fun to other people
i would say you you don't really know
what status you are until you
meet another person it's basically
interactive
that's how we judge it i guess you could
be low status to the wrong more
low status to the sofa you won't sit
back on it you sit there
with your toes pointing on the edge of
the sofa
yeah yeah it's true you could be you
could be
low status but we have to test it by
somebody coming into the room
if you then spread yourself a bit we
know that
your status is really higher
anyway it was something norman i think
wrote the horse whisperer and he
as a 13 year old boy watched horses wild
horses out on the prairie
and he discovered there was nothing at
all that a
horse did that wasn't significant
and we did the same thing we all
i got into this by asking actors to find
the smallest possible purpose in
relation to another actor
and for months i've been trying to get
human behavior
and they could do especially in germany
they could do wonderful things as actors
except look human
but then i said can you can you try to
be a little
teeny bit less important than the person
you're talking to
or a tiny bit more and there it was
human behavior
wow then for two weeks we suffered
because
you couldn't ask a question without
somebody saying why are you asking that
question and
all our secret maneuverings were exposed
and we became much friendlier
because friends play status
shifts for fun acquaintances can't do
that
you can't call your friends you can't
say get out your own cow
if you're an acquaintance only if it's a
friend
so if you make them play status games
they get much friendlier
then there's the problem with what do
you do when you let them out into
the world again which is not a very
friendly place
if they spent 10 days getting friendly
i never solved that
thank you strange delay on this like
that's just the technology is it
i shouldn't read it as a message we're
just in awe
of you sounds like you're bouncing off
um all right thank you uh tyler um
gonna take in luke
yeah thanks peter um hi keith i'm
wondering
it seems to me like for some people when
they get this
concept of status and sort of put on
these goggles
their whole world becomes darker and
more machiavelli and everything becomes
kind of unwholesome and unhealthy and it
becomes this really toxic thing
and then for some people not and when
you talk about status and improv that
was the first time that i'd really heard
that concept evoked in a way where i
felt like
oh but it could be okay that this is all
happening the
subterranean maneuvering and it could be
fun
and maybe i sort of answered my question
is there's play there but i wonder how
if you see people get kind of swallowed
up by this status beast
and if you kind of see a difference that
leads some people to
internalize this concept and kind of
metabolize it
if we're going to do
[Music]
if we're going to introduce status to
people
i usually warn them they're going to
feel odd for a while but that
after a couple of weeks everything had
just come back to normal
it just becomes part of everyday life
and i have a problem i haven't solved
and i can't really do it
now because but i was teaching
i gave a class to john marston in
australia
to at his school to 10 and 11 year olds
just experimentally to see what it could
be like
and i started with some status
master servant would be no right that's
not essentially a status thing
but then i i veered away from
it because i'm in the middle of telling
them
the secrets of human behavior and then i
thought
is it right to know this when you're age
how machiavellian are you going to get
so i had exactly the same feeling that
you had about it
but certainly for students and grown-ups
if they understand it
they go through a process where they
feel like robots
so everybody's like a robot because you
see you can see what the person's doing
and they have no knowledge of what
they're doing it's just that they're
doing their normal status stuff and
an awful thing is that you often assume
that you're playing a status that you're
not
like if you're afraid of other people
you think you're low status
but no if you're afraid of other people
you're probably high
to keep them at a distance keep them
away
repel them so when you start
playing the games just doing it for fun
you get inside
at the moment i'm thinking that probably
i wish that i'd
had this insight when i was age 10
so i'm tending to think that it's
probably a good thing but
so much you do some research on it
not much research in theaters mostly
people's opinion
it's because they you know they put
drama into the universities where it
doesn't really belong
it's all the arts instead of demanding
research where you might have learned
something
they just call your research the
way to le marble you sculpted or
something
i mean there's not research
and i'd like to know stuff i mean
so yeah thanks that really answers it
i'm
i don't know the fantasy of research is
like mapping out sort of
phases of understanding of status
there's sort of you know
unconscious and edward bond's play safe
was coming on
i was an associate director of the royal
court theatre
and i wrote to new society saying
this was going to be very interesting
sociologically
this is going to cause all kinds of
ripples
so could they consider it as a project
yeah
and what they did was they sent a drama
critic
they didn't understand anything and you
just wrote a review
that wasn't very much fun
i mean people can't imagine doing
research
i have nothing though if you did turn it
into a research project that you could
pretty easily suck the play out of it
well you could wire the audience up
i don't know just some sort of primitive
um
emotional you know something just
study skin oh yes that's right we did
once have uh
only 72 buttons to give out to the
audience
and the rest of the audience didn't have
the buttons so we had to stop it because
the guys without buttons would get
really annoyed
but then
you can see the numbers jump up and down
and that that's when i could explain to
my actors that i was actually right
and that what i was telling them was
correct
they'd kill an idea and the numbers
would go down to
10 from 72 or
they they do some other improvisation
fold
so i got i got much more confident then
so but as i would
i would like more facts but
i i get the feeling that
science books they give experiments
and that's interesting and that's real
but if i pick up a
i mean i never studied literature but if
i pick up one of those books
they quite often imitate science by
giving opinions in the footnotes
but to hell with opinion i want fact
that an opinion is not a fact
so i think they're imitating science but
it's a con i think i did whatever the
question was i'm not answering it
anymore yeah you answered it
oh okay
all right um andy
you had a question he
wrote two chapters on spontaneity and
narrative skill
um in these days when we converse with
people
often that we naturally disagree with
how can we use
spontaneous hang on narrative skills
you're a bit quiet
can you speak up i can't hear you i'm
gonna mute you andy and i'll i'll read
your question on your behalf
um so andy said uh how can spontaneity
and narrative skill
be used to help us better converse with
people we naturally disagree with
or maybe how they can be repurposed in
in domains outside of improv
i have no idea
there's always a temptation to make up
an answer but
not getting emotional with people i mean
it's
another thing it's being playful
uh it gets like life or death it's like
you know it's like people challenging
each other and
then they don't listen to anything
i just think if you could be playful
you must know people who are good at
that
and they're positive and friendly and
and they listen as most people don't
listen at all
ah psychiatry i can't answer that
all right uh peter s you have to
know what you don't know guys i mean
oh my god i'm deformed
my head goes this way but not that way
hey
ah this needs attending to after this
my god that's terrible i need rolfing
oh sorry it goes that way but not that
way
that's bad okay
beginning at the end guys
all right yeah great uh i'm curious
um if you believe it's possible and if
so how
can we improvise with nature or
non-human
systems like birds or trees
or streams or oceans or other
intelligences
like people playing jazz with birds
and you know something that's maybe
similar to the previous
question of like not a theater situation
or not a
not a standard jazz quartet based on a
blues
progression but how do we still extend
this idea of improv
i don't think this is quite what you
mean but
you can certainly
change your relationship to small
children or animals
if you consciously do things like break
eye contact and look back
no adult ever looked away from a small
child and looked back again
so it oh then if you go
if you get divorced and you're taking
your kid to the zoo the scenes people
think to do
you can liven up things for yourself
with
testing which animals are going to be
responsive to
breaking eye contact i broke eye contact
and looked back at the polar bears in
copenhagen zoo and they suddenly
perceived me as meat and they were
crawling and raging at the bars and i
had to go away because it was if i'd
thrown stones at them or something
but as for
i don't mean i like animism as a
attitude of mind which you sort of
talking about i think
i mean consciousness is so weird and it
it has evolved over
billions of years somehow
so maybe yeah i don't believe this but
the kind of ideas that come to me which
i don't believe in
are that it's like a
a universal something or other yeah i
mean
before there was consciousness there was
a universe so
what sense do we make of that i mean
oh i got a name from natalie on
smermoffs on my spoon off on my computer
hello yes we're
ah hello yeah we're still here someone
just
mistakenly mutant them muted themselves
you mean you couldn't hear me then oh we
heard you we heard you
wasn't very good answer i mean i'm in
sympathy with that
and i think it probably has a very good
effect on you
if you're playing jazz to a stream but
and i'd like the idea but i don't know
whether it's going to alter the
temperature of the stream
which we could test
who was it oliver sachs at age 12 had
two
sets of plants and he prayed over one
and he didn't pray over the other to see
if
it had any effect
it didn't nope but you can test things
out like that
who was it dalton the early psychologist
discovered that prayer had a negative
effect
because the royal family got prayed over
every sunday
so he looked at the health of the royal
family compared to normal
middle-class people and found that they
were dying sooner so
he published a little pamphlet saying
that prayer was negative
i thought i'd share that with you
frederick galton victorian times
edwardian
okay i'm going to read a question on
someone's behalf
they message me privately
how to get others to play when they are
not in play mode
so how to seduce people to play uh when
they're not feeling playful
well
be persistent i would think
start where they are
[Music]
some people just don't want to play
i mean think how much they've suffered
not to want to play really
i mean if you if you kept an ape sitting
in the desk for
18 years it would be cruelty to animals
but they don't think it's cruelty to us
uh what's the question i'm good it's
gone again
i have no short-term memory as you may
have noticed
uh the question was about play like how
to seduce people into play when they're
not feeling playful
we had an imaginary hole in front of the
door of my first classroom
so pissed some people off but some
people would come in and walk round the
hole
which was nice they'd come in the door
and the whole class would scream at them
to be careful of the whole
but some people can't drop their status
therefore they can't really play
i've often tried music sports
no not often but when i got to know a
musician i've often suggested it
music sports was a great entertainment
200 years ago
when all the musicians you couldn't be a
composer
if you didn't improvise it would have
been so strange i'm a composer but i
don't improvise
no you'd be a strange animal
i think the last great public improviser
was france list
and that's been a disaster for classical
music because
i mean stravinsky had improvised against
bartok
that could have led to some very
interesting
results and also classical music
wouldn't have lost contact
in the same way that it has with the
mass audience
i remember elizabeth luchen saying she
thought there were 200 people in england
who could understand her music and i
think she was
i think it was true yeah absolutely
there's a scene in in
mozart biography film
fiction with salieri's
villain he gave lessons to beethoven i
don't know if you know that i mean he
was good
salieri and changed the chute
chain redid his march
with amadeus you've seen that
no amadeus most famous
scene in that film i think but that was
normal
uh louis
schlosser garcia
was walking in the streets in vienna and
they said are you coming to the improv
sports tonight there's a guy coming here
there's a guy in from salzburg we're
going to show him
what we viennese composers can do
and he said nice i got a dinner
arrangement tonight
the next day lewis slosher met his
slosser
met his friend again and his friend said
whatever you do don't accept the
challenge for a little short
ugly bastard from salzburg called
beethoven
there's no way you can win so that was
music sports was a
very interesting thing with very good
effects and it loosened everything up
and it was playful and
and savage sometimes
beethoven once turned somebody's
cello score upside down and improvised
on it for
an hour until the other guy left in rage
but all kinds of most of the stuff on
this is in german
unfortunately and i don't read that but
there must be lots and lots of stuff
about music improvisations
anyway when you talk to is if you when
you say to your musician
this is a great thing to do
they'll say you mean i'll be judged
you say well it's a game you get winners
and losers
and then they lose interest and actors
used to be like that
it started off not with actors that
would never have happened
it started off with improvisers with my
taking my improvisation class out
if you're going to play a game you have
to be willing to lose
and not not to become a bad loser i mean
so part of being playful is
give and take and some people are just
clinging on by their
teeth to the wreckage and they can't
operate in any other way but
these things are very good for neurotics
if you can get them to play them
it's been used in vancouver and
with neurotic since and who is it
somebody was using it in utiborg in
sweden
that i know about no good for psychotics
but
teaching neurotics and people with
stuff like status transactions is very
good
gives them social skills that you know
they have no
access to normally
anyway i wrote that i've written all
that stuff out people can experiment
with it i
desperately tried to clarify it took me
10 years to write in pro mostly because
i
i couldn't get the last essay to be to
fit
finally i sent it in i was being
pestered by
yeah you don't normally get pestered by
publishers
unless they paid you a lot of money and
they didn't pay me any money
as a as an advance
so i finally sent it in
can't read it now
ah i seem to be nodding off here
somebody else yeah we we have uh um
about 10 more minutes so we'll have
maybe
squeezing two more questions two people
to go
um fool jeff you're up next
hello um i am playful
i'm playful sometimes but i get feedback
that
life is serious and
the best feedback might be that life is
serious play
do you have tips for balancing the
serious and the play
life is everything i mean the universe
is everything i mean
if you if you select you can prove the
universe is horrific
or kind of ecstatic you could be samuel
beckett or you could be william blake
i mean it's question which filth has you
put on it
what is everything yes
you do
you do select your experiences
and you do have a filter um
you like confirmation you don't like to
be contradicted
unless we're going to go through some
sort of revelation
uh so once you get set
where it's like all these these trump
guys
once they've sort of settled in that
he's a hero he can do pretty well
anything
totally screw them up and lie
and renege on all of his promises but
they'll still support him because it
would take a
huge paradigm shift i've never used that
word before
a huge change to
see what the guys really like so they'll
stick with him
as the ship goes down so
i'm not sure that's quite answering your
problem but
you have to try stuff uh
i don't i'm not i'm in favor of
instead of working out how to proceed
is to keep the spokes of the wheel keep
going down different spokes did you get
some effect
i wanted to teach children in this class
of
46 kids in battersea to enjoy writing
when i was my first class i always give
the worst class
to the new teacher it's a kind of um
initiation so you
to destroy your dreams you go in and
spend a year
with these monstrous kids that nobody
else wants
but i like them i thought yeah i mean it
didn't work with me
because i thought this i'd been a
christmas postman in battersea and i'd
so like the local kids
that i talked to in the street so i went
and became a teacher in battersea
and i had to go through some committee
to vet me
they were very interested in why i
wanted to go and teach you battersea
because nobody else had put that down
gavila wanted to teach in middle class
suburbs
but i'm losing the track again here
i was in the classroom with 46 kids what
was it
what was your question it must relate to
i was asking him oh yes
i had it okay serious serious play
every day i went in with another method
and
every day i failed and after six weeks
i hit the jackpot but i couldn't have
guessed before that it would have worked
i asked them to write about their dreams
nobody'd ever shown the slightest
interest in their dreams
but they were fascinated by their dreams
so suddenly all these kids wanted to
write and
they're yelling out words that they
can't spell and i'm writing on the
blackboard and
i got mass enthusiasm and
tonight when the writing came in i began
to think
other teachers were playing a joke on me
because
i'd never seen such interesting writing
from young kids
but that's how i that's that's my method
of preceding you
you don't decide on anything first you
try it out
and if it doesn't work you don't persist
you try something else
it's not this if you first
don't succeed try try it and try again
no
if you don't succeed give up try
something else
so i don't know whatever your problems
are
try lots of things try tickling them
that might work i mean who knows
today i'm going to tickle strangers and
see if that makes
changes their attitude to me
tomorrow i'll suggest to clean them and
see what happens
all right on friday i invite them to
tickle me
i mean you just keep keep trying stuff
and one day you hit something really
good
i mean the status stuff is trying to get
normal human behavior
i've been working on for years
even though i knew all that stuff it was
it was impossible to think of asking
adults
to change their status for some reason
then another course is used in almost
all drama schools good drama schools
it's a
it's universal because it's so valuable
it's so important and you know things
like
you know if you're an actor in a movie
it's really improvisation most of the
time
and you should learn this stuff you only
play one status you're so limited
you can only play handlers you can't
play the toilet cleaner or whatever
you're stuck so i think
also the status thing that
since we talked about status earlier
most important thing in status
is to learn to match the other person's
status
i would say that some of the questions
i've been asked before that's a good
answer too
if you can if you can learn to do that
you disarm them
there's a movie a movie star
he was um
who attributed his success to this game
tried going into agents or people like
spielberg high status and
they hated him he tried going in low
status
and they loved him but they wouldn't
give him any work
he tried matching status and you said
keith
now they think i'm one of them now he is
yeah so it's really important
it's not easy to match status with a
high status person
i have a friend who knows this story who
occasionally emails me saying
i was trying it i was trying it was so
and so bad
i did it for five minutes and then i
crumbled
so i would recommend to as a basic
social skill
practicing matching status you could
start off
with toddlers for a start
toddlers who teach you lots of things
they'll teach you how to smile for a
start i mean
it's quite nice to start with
three-year-old kids
share eye contact see the same status
see normally status as a seesaw goes up
and down
but the closer you get it the more
intimate the acting gets
and the more they feel you're one of
them you're one of their people
and they don't know what's doing it they
just feel warmth towards you
they should teach it to detectives
interview people in those little rooms
they confess in 20 minutes
ah next you must be
time must be almost over my goodness
yeah uh
time is up actually um
we have uh would you like one more
question or would you like to end it
here but i'm very glad i told you that
last thing
because that really is the secret of
training status
be the same as the person you're talking
to
and you have all kinds of techniques for
moving up and down you can
keep your head stiller or you can bite
your bottom nipping giggle or you can do
those sorts of status techniques where
you can change the balance
and you can if you become an expert on
it people like you
and yeah you're one of them
yeah i feel like that's that's my final
advice to your
organization next time you meet you can
all try it
you'll be so suspicious of each other
are you doing it
no no that's wrong
do you do you recommend any games for us
to play here at the stoa
if you get about 15 or 20 people
it's quite good to divide them into two
groups
and give one group at some low status
thing to practice
and the other group some high status
thing
purely doing it from the outside one
group holds eye contact
the other group
breaks eye contact and takes quick looks
back
and you mingle and then you
change around and you try three or four
of these for a while
they might like dolphin training
i got it from a book by some famous now
famous animal trainer
it's what they used to do in sea world
in florida i think
uh i don't know what i've forgotten
about the hell it is wait a minute
my filing clerk is so slow these days
yeah you get some
some quality like
we want you to take your hat off
but you don't know that
so then the audience goes beep beep if
you go anywhere near
if you put your hand up in the air
towards your head you get lots of beeps
such a simple game they used to make
people do that until they were good at
it
before they left them anywhere near a
dolphinic
except to clean the tank
so that was a basic training for dolphin
trainers
and they were good because they had
dolphins that could
be out of the water with their tail
going like an outboard motor
no no dolphin had ever done that since
the
history of the world
that your audience would be very bad at
beeping people
they'll beat them to put their hands up
here i mean they'll
they'll be and you tell the person who's
playing the game that it's not for them
for training the audience
that gives them more confidence but
that's
an important game and it's great to
start any session off with
puts people in a good mood
dolphin training i bet if you
it's probably on the internet
everything's on the internet
but i never typed in dolphin training
i typed in keith johnstone in cabbage
the other day
and yet there it is keith john stone in
cabbage
i couldn't believe it ah
this t i live too long really and this
technology is all
too weird i mean come on
did want to die at 72 that's before this
new technology got started
and that's 15 years ago i totally failed
i failed everything except teaching
improvisation and
i never wanted to do that i mean it's
ridiculous
well all right keith uh i think we'll
end here
um any closing thoughts for us here at
the store
no i'll keep i keep dribbling on for
ages
we want the obvious we all taught that
what we have inside us
isn't good enough i mean
the obvious is so difficult yeah that
status was the obvious
it took me ah such a long time
i think i started in 68
i did it finally in about 62.
god and as soon as you find it of course
of course it's so obvious
but teacher teaches teachers don't
respect the obvious
you know either i would like that as a
bumper sticker
if you think of something clever to say
say something else that's what i tell
improvisers
because i'm hunting for the obvious
think inside the box for god's sake
if you think outside the box no one can
work with you
it's a good spot to end um
thank you so much keith for coming to
the store
uh we'd love to have you back anytime
you'd like
oh my god i have absolutely nothing else
to say
all right everyone uh we're gonna close
out here uh i dropped some links in the
chat the website for
more events the patreon and the sub
stack
we have an event coming up tonight
called communitas club where we're
launching a new series where we
investigate various
conversations and we're definitely going
to um
[Music]
do some status games here at the store
we'll figure it out goodbye
bye keith i don't know how to get rid of
you
[Music]
you're stuck with us
every button you can't find the door
yes that's right yeah it's a good game
room oh i found the mute
yeah started right next to the invisible
okay everyone i'm gonna play some music
so we can just all
enjoy this together